<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on Pallavi Rajain</title>
    <link>https://PalRajain.github.io/project/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on Pallavi Rajain</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2016 Pallavi Rajain</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Jun 2016 14:06:35 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://PalRajain.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Women Entrepreneurship: A Study of Contribution, Challenges and Potential</title>
      <link>https://palrajain.github.io/project/women-entrepreneurship/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jun 2016 14:06:35 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://palrajain.github.io/project/women-entrepreneurship/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Women leadership seems to be ideal for women seeking participation in the country’s economic development, because of certain factors. The emergent role of women is considered to be closely linked to social, cultural, religious and psychological variables and these changes seem to have become acceptable norms in the context of women at work in the Indian scenario today with more and more women participating in the economic development. As such women both in education and non-education sectors to fulfill their aspirations of doing something concrete both economically and socially. In sum, the problem of entrepreneurship among women is a question of the family outlook on the role to be played by the women, and the estimation of capabilities by women themselves. Much depends upon the courage and determination of women to become entrepreneurs and with the various facilities offered by Government, banks and financial institutions to women, they should now start setting up business ventures in large numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An entrepreneur is one of the most important segments of economic growth. They are the ones who have shown that genius is sweat and toil and sacrifice and that natural resources gain value only by the ingenuity and labor of man. Basically, an entrepreneur is a person who is responsible for setting up a business or an enterprise. In fact, he is one who has the initiative, skill for innovation and who looks for high achievements. He is a catalytic agent of change and works for the good of people. He puts up new green field projects that actually creates wealth, opens up employment opportunities and fosters other sectors. The entrepreneur is now a critical factor in the socio-economic change and a key man who envisages new techniques, new line of production, new products and co-ordinates all other activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Freedom depends on economic conditions even more than political. If a woman is not economically free and self-earning, she will have to depend on her husband or someone else, and dependents are never free’. These were the ideas of Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru, first Prime Minister of India, which vividly highlight the importance of economic independence of women. These views are antagonistic to the laws of Manu written much early either before or during the Christan Era which stress the need to control women because of the ‘evils’ of female character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;“When women move forward, the family moves, the village moves”. These words of Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru are often repeated because it is accepted facts that only when women are in the mainstream of progress, can any economic and social development be meaningful.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Woman entrepreneur is regarded as a person who accepts a challenging role to quench her ambition to become something, such as to be economically independent by making suitable adjustments in both family and social life. They are constantly on the look-out for new and innovative ways which lead to strong economic participation. Their adeptness, skill and knowledge, their acumen in business and a pushing desire to do something positive are among the reasons for women to establish and mange organized industries and take up challenging ventures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contribution of women in the economic development process can be mainly classified into four segments namely:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Employment in the organized sector&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Employment in unorganized sector&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self-employment and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Entrepreneurs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;need-for-the-study&#34;&gt;Need for the Study&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Women are increasingly turning to entrepreneurship which is a significant factor for economic growth. The government and the semi government organizations are playing important role in mobilizing women empowerment through different programs. The number of women entrepreneurs is increasing and further it is expected to increase much more.

A lot of data is available on entrepreneurial characteristics and motivations of men but very little data is available regarding women entrepreneurs. Little research has been done in India to probe into questions like, what motivates women to become entrepreneurs? What kind of enterprises would women like to take up? What are the support systems available for them? How do they go about managing their business? What discriminations and obstacles they face and how much success they experience? Can an attempt is made to answer these questions one realizes that at this stage these questions have been only partially answered.  Even the little data that is available is on the potential women entrepreneurs rather than the operational entrepreneurs.

 Although a number of developmental projects belonging to better roads, electricity and agricultural growth were the aims of the state’s policy/planning of developmental programmes in the initial decade. A very little was thought of promoting women entrepreneurship. Hence, it (women entrepreneurship) is a recent phenomenon to explore and to streamline their contribution in the economic activity and the development of the state. Even if some women entrepreneurs have taken up the responsibility of launching their enterprises at some point of time, their contribution to entrepreneurship was not a matter of any serious consideration/interest or appreciation in the society. That is why, to evaluate their contribution, however in insignificant it may have been sounded in the eyes of society, their contribution must not be overlooked while assessing the economic progress of Haryana. That is why, the selection/adoption of this long ignored topic with a view to elevate the concept of women entrepreneurship as a highly significant cause of the day.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;scope-of-the-study&#34;&gt;Scope of the Study&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Haryana is one of the most important industrial states in the northern India having the many industrial cities. The industrial growth in Haryana has been phenomenal. The state has a diversified industrial base. It is one of the premier industrial centers of the country. Quite a good number of big units in the private and joint sectors are also here. Besides large units, significant growth has been found in small and ancillary industrial units and commercial and trading establishments. The state with has good infrastructural facility. Offers sound prospects for industrial development. The study focused on the critical appraisal of the government policies, organizations and programmes concerned with the promotion and development of women entrepreneurship.

Women entrepreneurship in Haryana is of recent origin. Though trading activities like sale of vegetables and fruits have been taken up by the adjoining rural women since long, entrepreneurship on modern lines has been found in industry, trade and service concerns from only one decade or so. So far, there has not been even a single study made by any individual or institution on women entrepreneurship in Haryana State. It has been impossible even for making a census list of women entrepreneurs in Haryana since no organized effort either from the government or other agencies was made. Hence, women managing and type of business activity, be it manufacturing, trading or service is to be targeted for the study. As the study is to be proposed on women entrepreneurs and not on self-employed women, only women enterprises big enough and requiring managerial and entrepreneurial abilities on the part of the women are to be considered. The study will propose on operating women entrepreneurs to be able to access their performance and hence only enterprises which were started and in operation after women decade or after the 1991 were considered. In the light of this, it is thought that a modest attempt in a systematic way for studying the different aspects of women entrepreneurship in Haryana State would be a good beginning. The researcher will also evince special interest for this study.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After going through the theoretical framework and reviewing the literature on women entrepreneurship, the researcher reached to the conclusion that the study should be made on the aspect of women entrepreneurship consisting the performance and problems of women entrepreneurship and the motivation factor behind women entrepreneurship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;objectives-of-the-study&#34;&gt;Objectives of the Study&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;The broad objective of the study is to analyze the patterns of women entrepreneurship and the specific problems being faced by women in business. The specific objectives of the study are:-
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To portray a profile of women entrepreneurs in India.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To study the economic contribution of women entrepreneurs in economic growth of Haryana.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To analyze the various problems and challenges faced by women entrepreneurs in setting up and running their enterprises&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To analyze the major strength, weakness, environmental opportunity and threats.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To document existing government policies, programmes and the involvement of support agencies in promoting women&amp;rsquo;s entrepreneurship.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To suggest a framework for the promotion of women entrepreneurship in Haryana.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>